Inventory of the This Century Art Gallery Records 1959-2001
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
This Century Art Gallery Records 1959-2001
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2002.15
5.00
The records of This Century Art Gallery include office, financial, and personal files from various board members and officers, Board Minutes, printed material such as promotional material and newsletters, artist/exhibit information, inventory notebooks, daily logs, and loose papers.
This Century Art Gallery; Sherman, Roger; Shiflett, Glenna Graves; Williamsburg Historic Records Association (Williamsburg, Va.) arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from This Century Art Gallery via Glenna Shiflett and Michael Kerby on 03/31/2002.
Historical Note
This Century Art Gallery - Williamsburg exhibits a wide variety of contemporary paintings, sculpture, and crafts by outstanding regional and national artists. The Gallery, adjacent to Merchants Square and the Historic Area in Williamsburg, Virginia, occupies a unique 1920 Sears Roebuck house that was modernized in the 1980s.
The Gallery is a nonprofit organization that is wholly volunteer-operated. Members give their time generously to manage Gallery business and to run the many programs it offers.
Membership fees and sales help support the Gallery. Major exhibitions open monthly with a preview reception for members and their guests.
The Gallery was named Twentieth Century Gallery when it opened in 1959 and is affiliated with the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts.
--From the Web site for This Century Art Gallery, July 2007
Scope and Contents
The records of This Century Art Gallery include office, financial, and personal files from various board members and officers, Board Minutes, printed material such as promotional material and newsletters, artist/exhibit information, inventory notebooks, daily logs, and loose papers.
The group of office files that arrived as a unit, already in folders, were kept together and the original file names retained. These Office Files contain many newspaper clippings and promotional printed material. In the front of each Office File folder are 3 subfolders: one each for the original newspaper clippings, the copies of the clippings and original printed material.
The personal files of the Board members and officers included numerous duplications, particularly of monthly financial reports, board minutes and quarterly Bulletins. These records were pulled and combined in date order into the file headings of Treasurer's Reports, Board Minutes or Printed Material - Bulletins. At least 2 copies of each report were kept. If there were notes on any of the reports, it was kept. In a few instances, a board member's or officer's file contained material not duplicated elsewhere. These files were kept intact (except for removal of the duplicated reports) and the name of the board member or officer is noted on the folder as part of the heading. Files of unknown members that had very little material left in them after removing duplicate copies where merged into a folder entitled Board of Directors - Correspondence.
Some files for a specific event (exhibit or show) arrived in notebooks. These files were put into new folders with their original order and heading maintained. New folder headings were created to pull together material on artists, exhibits and shows that were found either loose or scattered through individual files.
Because Roger Sherman had made notes on many of the papers he gathered to help him write the history of the Gallery, they have been left together, but filed within the categories used for the rest of the collection, with his name as part of the folder heading. The exceptions are his actual drafts of the history, which are filed under his name.
Inventory located in Box 1.
Arrangement of Materials
The files have been grouped into five categories: Financial, Board Matters, Artists/Exhibits, Office Files (original headings) and Office Files (artificially grouped).
Additional Information
Related Materials
Mss. Acc. 2006.19 Glenna Shiflett Papers.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
This Century Art Gallery (Williamsburg, Va.); Twentieth Century Gallery (Williamsburg, Va.); Virginia Museum of Fine Arts.; Williamsburg Arts Council (Williamsburg, Va.)
Genre/Form of Material:
Agendas (administrative records); Correspondence; Deeds; Financial records; Fliers (printed matter); Minutes; Reports
Occupation:
Artists
Topical Term:
Art Gallery; Williamsburg (Va.)--History--20th century.; Williamsburg (Va.)--History.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- (1)
    Series 1: Office Files
  - Office Files (1)
      Subseries 1: Office Files, Artificially Created
    - Office Files, Artificially Created, 1959-2001 (1)
      Office related files including correspondence, membership lists, logbooks, day book, promotion and publicity files, procedures, volunteer records, lease and other building related material.
      Most of the material in this series was pulled together from loose material or scattered records to create an artificial grouping of office related files.
      Subseries 2: Office Files
    - Office Files, 1959-1984 (1, 2)
      These files have been kept in their original order with their original file headings. They contain many newspaper clippings and promotional printed material. In the front of each Office File folder are 3 sub folders: one each for the original newspaper clippings, the copies of the newspaper clippings and original printed material.
- (2)
    Series 2: Financial Information
  - Financial Information, 1965-1966, 1968-1969, 1971-1974, 1977-2001 (2)
    This series includes annual reports, bank records, tax records, business records, invoices, treasurer’s reports and sales records.
- (3)
    Series 3: Board of Directors Material
  - Board of Directors Material, 1959-1985, 1987, 1989-2001 (3)
    The Board of Directors Material was pulled together from various personal files, loose papers and groups of minutes. The series includes by-laws, job descriptions, member packets, handbooks, correspondence and minutes.
- (4)
    Series 4: Roger Sherman's Files
  - Roger Sherman's Files, 1959-1980 (4)
    Drafts of History of Twentieth Century Gallery by Roger Sherman, with notes and chronology.
    About 1980, Roger Sherman gathered material from the office files of the Twentieth Century Gallery to help him write a history of the Gallery. As part of the Gallery Papers, these files were included in a box of Roger Sherman material. Since the files had been removed from the original office files, they were returned to the main collection during processing except for the materials that had notes by Roger Sherman or were written by Roger Sherman.
- (5)
    Series 5: Artists, Exhibits, Shows and Inventories
  - Artists, Exhibits, Shows and Inventories, 1984-2000 with gaps (5)
    These materials arrived loose, mixed in with unrelated files, in folders or in notebooks. They are grouped by artists, exhibits and inventory sheets. Some workshop material is included.
- (6)
    Series 6: Addition Acc. 1997.47
  - Addition Acc. 1997.47, 1959-1984 (6)
    Ten items relating to the history of the Twentieth Century Gallery in Williamsburg when it was located on Nicholson Street. Founded in 1959, its first President was Glenna Shiflett. Includes list of members, board members, film society membership and list of members of the Junior Woman's Club. 1959-1984.
    Series 7: Addition Acc. 2004.17
  - Addition Acc. 2004.17, 1959-1987 (6)
    Scrapbook of Twentieth Century Gallery which covers 1959-1969, created by Glenna Graves Shiflett.
    Folder with a few records from 1974-1987, including a January 13, 1981 deed from Thomas B. Shiflett and Glenna G. Shiflett to Glenna G. Shiflett, Lot #5 and part of Lot #6 in West Williamsburg Heights, Williamsburg, Virginia.
    Series 8: Addition Acc. 2005.52
  - Addition Acc. 2005.52, 1978-1981 (6)
    2005.52
    List of members, 1978, of Williamsburg Arts Council, bank statement, 1981, concerning Williamsburg Arts Council and a March 4, 1980 letter with appraisal of 501 Richmond Road, owned by Thomas B. Shiflett and wife.